Welcome to a public affair and WRT 89.9 FM. This is Monday edition of the program hosted
by Yuri Rashkin. Today the subject of our conversation is torture. It is not a subject
that is pleasing and it's a difficult conversation, but I think one that needs to be had when we
have good reason for it. Here's the situation. We're going to be spending today's program
reviewing, doing something unusual that I don't think this program or most programs
ever really do. We're going to be concentrating not necessarily on a book, but on a review
of a book. And so here's the situation. Well, the Navy Institute has published a
book called The CIA Response to the Senate Intelligence Committee's Study of its Detention
and Interrogation Program. With such an exciting title, this includes contributors,
include former CAE Director George Tenet, Porter Goss, Michael Hayden, former Deputy
Director John McLaughlin, and Michael Morrill, former Counterterrorist, Center Deputy Director
Jay Philip Mudd, former Chief Legal Counsel John Rizzo, and former head of clandestine
service Jose Rodriguez, Jr. Well, that sounds like an interesting book right there, doesn't
it? At this point, I'm excited to welcome to the program my guest is today for this
hour is John Kuriyaku. And it's nice when you have a Wikipedia page dedicated to
your guest so that you can look up exactly, see, you know, who you are speaking to.
And so I will read a little bit from John's Wikipedia page. He was a CAE analyst and
case officer, senior investigator for the Senate Foreign Relations Committee and counterterrorism
consultant for ABC News and author. He was the first year as government official to confirm
in December 2007 that waterboarding was used to interrogate Al Qaeda prisoners, which he
described as torture. On October 22nd, 2012, Kuriyaku pleaded guilty to disclosing classified
information about a fellow CAE officer that connected the covert operative to a
specific operation. He was the first person to pass classified information to a reporter,
although the reporter did not publish the name of the operative. John Kuriyaku, welcome
to a public affair. How are you doing? Thank you so much for having me. I'm doing very
well. Thank you. It's really exciting to have you on the program. So we have a
book coming out and the book basically is just if it is their response to a Senate
report that says there was torture and was it, you know, there were no results to show
its effectiveness. Yeah, and I would remind listeners as well that the Senate report, whether
or not it had Republican support, was irrelevant. It was based solely on primary source documentation.
That is contemporaneous CIA reporting from the field. This was information that came
from the horse's mouth. And with that in mind, do you feel that the information is
reliable? And what are your thoughts on the book that's going to be put out here
shortly by all the CAE directors? Well, I do believe that the Senate report was
reliable and it was entirely consistent with the CIA Inspector General's report that
was written in 2005 and released in 2009. That report also found that torture did
not work, that actionable intelligence was not collected, and that no attacks were
disrupted and no American lives were saved by torture. How can we prove the opposite, you know?
Right. How do you prove a negative? And so because of that, we have this book that's
come out written by three former CIA directors, as you said, and a bevy of
other senior, former senior officials. But my position is that the reason that they've
written this book is not necessarily to refute the Senate torture report, but to
try to save their own reputation. The torture program is their legacy. It's
what history will know them by. And I think that they think that if they keep
repeating the lie that torture worked over and over and over again, that the
American people will be either too gullible or too stupid to appreciate the truth.
Is that a matter of public perception or legal liability, do you think?
I think it's really a matter of public perception because for many of the crimes
outlined in the Senate torture report, the statutes of limitations have expired.
So I think this is really about these men's place in history.
Listeners, give us a call. What your thoughts are on torture. Do you feel this is
something that is justified and something that ever works? Give us a call.
608-256-2001. And frankly, I think considering our guest, I'd like to
specifically hear from people who feel that torture is justified and is
effective in certain situations because it's always nice to have a couple
of different points of view. John, can you talk a little bit about your
background with CIA? Sure. I spent just under 15 years with the CIA. I spent the
first half of that career as an analyst working on the Middle East and
primarily on Iraq. Served overseas in that capacity as well. And then in 1997 I
switched to counterterrorism operations, working to recruit spies to
steal secrets and to infiltrate groups like Al Qaeda to disrupt future
terrorist attacks. After September 11th I became the chief of CIA counterterrorism
operations in Pakistan. And I led a raid, I led a series of raids in March 2002 that
resulted in the capture of Abu Zubaydah, who at the time we believed was the
number three in Al Qaeda. That turned out to not be correct, although he was a
very senior logistician and he created and maintained Al Qaeda's
training camps in southern Afghanistan. I left the CIA in 2004, went into the
private sector for five years, and then I became the senior investigator on the
Senate Foreign Relations Committee. Everything changed for me at least in
2012. In 2007 I went on ABC News and I gave an interview to Brian Ross and I
said three things. I said that the CIA was torturing its prisoners, that torture
was official U.S. government policy, and that the policy had been approved of and
signed by the president. And so the FBI began investigating me. The
investigation lasted four years. I didn't know I was under investigation.
And in January of 2012 I was charged with five felonies, including three
counts of espionage coming out of that interview. Four of the charges were
finally dropped and I took a plea to a lesser charge of violating the
Intelligence Identities Protection Act of 1982. I was sentenced to 30 months in
prison. I served 23 those months and was released earlier this year.
What is your opinion of the Obama administration and its efforts on dealing
not just with terrorism but with torture? Well, I think the Obama
administration really has done very little to address the torture issue. It
wasn't until just this past spring that Diane Feinstein, the senior senator from
California and John McCain, Republican of Arizona, joined together to sponsor a
bill that was very quickly passed into law that would finally and
definitively ban torture by U.S. government entities. What President
Obama did when he was elected president is find an executive order banning
torture, but that didn't necessarily have the effect of law in that any
future president could have just signed an executive order
re-implementing the torture program. So what we really needed was a
law and the impetus for that law did not come from the White House. It
came from the Congress. And now we have a law. Are people going to be held
responsible? Well, that's really the $64,000 question and I think the answer
is clearly now no. No one will be held responsible. As I said a few minutes ago,
the statute of limitations on many of these crimes have expired and the
president has made it clear that he wants to, as he put it, look forward
not backward and nobody involved in torture. Even those officers who killed
prisoners during the course of interrogation, even they will not be
held responsible for their crimes. What message do you feel the sends? Well,
it's just so hypocritical of us. The State Department is mandated every year
with writing a human rights report on every country with which we have
diplomatic relations. And I was an embassy human rights officer when I was
serving in the Middle East and we would go to the Ministry of Justice and the
Ministry of Interior and to the office of the Prime Minister and we would
complain about human rights abuses that we had documented. And we would tell
them, look, you risk having a cough of American aid. You risk having
military aid cut off if you don't improve your human rights practices.
Well, in fact, we were doing things that were much worse than most of these
other countries did.
So it's very hypocritical of us to talk about human rights and to profess to be this shining
beacon on a hill, you know, who's supporting and demanding around the world respect for
human rights when we don't respect human rights.
And I'm talking here only about torture.
I'm not talking about things like solitary confinement or the death penalty or other
domestic issues.
I'm talking specifically about torturing prisoners in secret prisons overseas.
See, this is the thing that...
The thing that I think most of us human beings who live in a lot of comfort don't think about
is I think how little it takes for a human being to feel tortured.
And that's legitimate.
I mean, you can leave a light bulb on in a room with no windows 24 hours a day.
That's torture.
I agree with you.
You know, in fact, we talk so much about waterboarding.
And certainly waterboarding is a terrible thing.
But the CIA was using techniques that I believe were even worse than waterboarding on prisoners.
One of those was sleep deprivation.
And as you say, they leave bright lights on 24 hours a day in a windowless cell.
They bombard the cell with hard rock music.
I'm not talking about forcing a prisoner to be awake for 24 hours or 48 or 72.
I'm talking about forcing a prisoner to remain awake for 10 days, 12, 14 days even.
We know now that some prisoners lose their minds to the point where they're not able
to participate in their own defenses.
And to me, that's torture.
And another thing that we were doing, and this actually resulted in the death of two prisoners,
was what's called the cold cell, where we strip a prisoner naked.
We chain him to an eyeball in the ceiling so he can't sit or kneel.
We chill the cell to 50 degrees, and then every hour we throw ice water on him.
Well, that kills you.
Your body can't take that kind of hypothermia.
And how George Tennant and Mike Hayden and Porter Goss and their minions
think that this is torture is just a mystery to me.
You're listening to WRT, Monday edition of a public affair.
This is Yuri Rashkin and my guest is former CIA counterterrorism officer John Kiriako.
On a lighter note, I think one of the forms of torture is to listen to talk radio
and not be able to participate.
On that note, I'm excited to welcome to program a caller.
Thomas, what's your question or comment for our guest?
Hello?
Yes. My name is Thomas.
Yes.
Okay. When you called up, you said you wanted to hear from people who think torture works.
Absolutely.
And I'm going to give you my opinion on that.
The reason torture works is because it puts fear into all the other prisoners
and it puts fear into the American people so it's easier for them to go to war.
And the second reason that works is because then we can say we have prevented,
we have prevented espionage in this country
or we have prevented an attack by terrorists in this country
and therefore in order to preserve our way of life,
we have to get all the information on everybody that lives here
and that's how we're keeping you free.
And so torture works in that sense.
Thomas, it almost sounds a little like you're being a little sarcastic here, I guess, to me.
I am not being sarcastic.
I'm trying to tell you that's the way it works on the general population
and even some of the people who do the torturing.
So I'm not being sarcastic.
So you're saying it has a certain effect and that's the effect that it has?
Yes.
Right?
It's easy to do and thank you for the program.
Thank you very much for the call.
John, what are your thoughts?
Well, you know, that's, in a funny way, I have to agree with the caller
because it does have a way of cowing the American people.
You know, when former Attorney General Eric Holder went before the Senate Judiciary Committee
and was asked by, I think it was Senator Rand Paul,
does the President have the right to murder American citizens with drones?
And Attorney General Holder said yes.
And then the Senator asked, does he have the right to murder American citizens with drones on U.S. territory?
And the Attorney General wouldn't respond to that question.
Then I think that what the caller is saying is probably true.
We are frightened into following our leadership like Lemmings right off the edge of the cliff.
And I think that many of our leaders probably want that to be the case.
If we presume that torture doesn't work to get information
and you worked for Central Intelligence Agency,
what is an effective way of getting information out of people in your opinion?
Well, as much as CIA officers hate the FBI institutionally,
going back to the creation of the CIA in the 1940s,
we have to give credit where credit is due.
The FBI really is the federal government's elite interrogation force.
They really know how to do it and to do it successfully.
And the way you do it successfully is to build a rapport
and a relationship with the person that you're interrogating.
This takes time, but the FBI and military interrogators
succeeded wildly with this method in the immediate aftermath of the Second World War
with German scientists and German military leaders.
We should have done that in the so-called war on terror.
Instead, we were impatient and we believed that we could get the same kind of information
through torture that we could have through rapport building.
And frankly, we didn't.
All right, we have a caller on the line.
Keith, welcome to the program.
What is your question or comment for our guest?
Oh, hi, yes, it's a great honor to speak with John.
Thank you.
I'm wondering if you had decided whether you actually thought about going public with this very long
and did you ever imagine that you would be prosecuted for actually revealing this information?
And did you ever think about doing what Edward Snowden did and leaving in...
You know, I did not give this...
I'm embarrassed to say I did not give this a lot of thought before I did it.
Brian Ross called me in December 2007 and said that he had a source
who said that I had tortured Abu Zubeda.
I said that that was absolutely untrue.
I was the only person who was kind to Abu Zubeda.
I sat with him next to his bed.
I held his hand.
We talked about our lives.
I never laid a hand on Abu Zubeda or on any other prisoner.
And Brian Ross said, well, you're free to come on to the show and defend yourself.
And I was weighing whether or not I should do this.
And at that same time, President Bush gave a press conference
in which he looked right at the camera and he said, we do not torture.
Well, I knew that that was a lie.
We had been torturing people for years.
And then later in the week, President Bush said, if there is torture,
it's the result of a rogue CIA officer.
And I thought, oh my God, they're going to pimp on me.
So I called Brian Ross and I agreed to the interview.
And when he asked me a direct question about whether or not we were torturing prisoners,
I gave him a direct answer and I said yes.
When I was first arrested, I went to see an attorney,
Jeff Lynn Radak, who specializes in whistleblower defense.
And I said to her, listen, I should tell you off the bat, I'm not a whistleblower.
And she said, oh yes, you are.
She said, no whistleblower thinks he's a whistleblower.
But there's a legal definition of whistleblowing.
And it's bringing to light any evidence of waste, fraud, abuse or illegality.
She said, you're the poster boy for whistleblowers.
So I decided to fight.
And I made a decision that I was going to go trial, which I ended up not doing.
But I fought for an entire year.
I didn't know it at the time, but Ed Snowden was closely following my case.
And then after I took a plea and went to prison, Snowden made his revelations.
Well, he told The New York Times in 2014 that Tom Drake, the NSA whistleblower,
and I inspired him to go public, that he saw evidence of waste, fraud, abuse and illegality.
And he decided to say something about it.
So in that respect, I'm very proud that I had at least that influence.
And to tell you the honest to God's truth, I like to think that I have had a small role
in the abolition of torture in the United States.
And so if you asked me if it was worth it, it was worth it.
And I would do it again.
John, do you feel that there is torture going on now by CIA?
You know, I want to say no, but I know the CIA.
I was there for 15 years.
And I know that some members of the CIA's leadership are what I think many of us would call sociopaths.
So because there's...
often disagreement over what exactly constitutes torture
i'm going to say yes i think they're probably still is torture going on
somewhere in the world
uh... at the hands of
of american officials
do you see or situation scenario where there is central intelligence agency
that does not engage in torture
i do
you know we we had a period of that briefly
from uh... from around nineteen seventy six
with the church uh... committee hearings
uh... until september eleventh
and uh... as jetlin redacted says uh... i want my september tenth country back
you know i remember at the c i a in the nineteen ninety
uh... there were very hard and fast rules
in place dealing with with human rights and if if we were targeting for
recruitment an individual who had
uh... a personal history of disrespect for human rights we were not allowed to
recruit him
it didn't matter the kind of information he had but we had to respect
human rights
and not just u s human rights laws but international law
that all came down to september eleventh and i don't think it changed for the
better
can that you know we need to go with another caller but i wanted to ask you
can you just to follow your line of thinking
is if you have
uh... you know the c i a that doesn't take people with uh... torturous
past
well you know
and then we are attacked in nine eleven can argument be made that we should have
uh... paid more attention to that information maybe there wouldn't be
nine eleven
i don't think so i think an argument can be made
that we should have
focused uh... more intensely and concentrated
uh... our our budget and our manpower on
developing human source intelligence
the root the reason why
we didn't disrupt the september eleventh attack is because we have no
sources inside al-qaeda
and al-qaeda had been around for years
and we had never been able to infiltrate the group
so if we had focused more on infiltrating the group
i think we could have disrupted the attack
you're listening to w r t public affair monday edition this is your iraskin
my guest is former c a counterintelligence counterterrorism officer
john kiriako and uh... scott welcome to the program what is your
question or comment for a guest
thank you uh... and i'd like to thank uh... your guests uh... for his
courage coming forward uh...
i think people like tom strake edward snowden and your guest today are true
american heroes and i let everyone know what that i speak to about this topic
i'd like to go back to the senate intelligence report
i believe it was just about exactly a year ago how prior to the
first uh... real uh... release
of any information in the report
it became known that the c a a had been hacking into senate
intelligence committee staff computers
spying uh... in the words of uh...
uh... set then senator mark u dot they like to come this the c i a like to
congress they like to the american people
uh... they destroyed evidence in the senate intelligence committee uh...
investigation and they threatened the senate intelligence staff
and uh... nothing is actually nothing has come of this
uh... five-person panel including i think former senator dornan was
uh...
put together to investigate what should be done with the idea that there are
almost uh... investigation said yes three agents and two lawyers
in the c i a responsible for this
uh... the five-person panel uh... convene for a while and said
i think
and uh... i have contacted senator balman's office
it's starting a year ago
and said what do you think about the c a
buying on the senate
and uh...
you know breaking laws
and what are you gonna do about it and to this day a year later
on my the response from senator balman has been absolutely nothing
zero
and uh... you know people like your
guest today are a hundred
uh... people with snone was a little five they claim he was a spy and he was
going to sell the information to the soviet and whoever he could get
you know top dollar from
these people are vilified they're prosecuted and incarcerated
and the criminals in the c i a are scott free
any comments please
but thank you thank you so much for your comment you know this is
this is perfectly
i i i i i i i i i i i honestly don't believe that we've seen this kind of
behavior
and then lack of response
uh... since the nixon administration
what you've described really
uh...
is a series of crimes against the american people
for the c i a to
by on
staffers cleared
senate staffers
for them to act into the senate
uh... computer system
for them to
The elite information that had been provided to the Senate in response to a subpoena.
These are all felonies.
This is obstruction of justice, it's wire fraud, it's probably espionage.
But this is something that I've learned the hard way.
And believe me, I believed in the whole hope and change thing back in 2008.
I proudly voted for Barack Obama, I went to the inauguration, I held up the signs.
But this is what the Obama administration has become.
It's become an administration of hypocrisy.
If you have four shiny stars on your shoulder, or if you're a friend of the president, or
if you are a senior official, for example in the CIA, and you commit a crime, no problem.
But if you leak information, especially to the press that embarrasses the administration,
you're going to be charged with espionage and your life is going to be ruined.
Let me tell you, from two weeks after I made my revelation on ABC News, I have been audited
by the IRS every single year since 2007.
I ended up being charged with five felonies including three counts of espionage for going
on ABC News and talking about torture.
The federal government took my pension, I had a million dollars in that pension,
19 plus proud years of federal service.
I lost my home, I lost my job, I lost everything.
I had to sell my personal possessions to pay my attorneys and I still owe them $880,000.
That's what happens if you leak information that embarrasses this administration.
But if you're General David Petraeus, you get off with a slap on the wrist.
If you're General James Cartwright, who allegedly leaked classified information about the Stuxnet
virus to the New York Times, you get off scot-free.
Don't forget that he was always known in administration circles as the president's favorite general.
So there really are two standards in this administration.
Those who are with them and those who are not with them, and the ones not with
them, are going to be ruined.
It sounds like you're with us or you're against us, you know, was an approach that was adopted
by both Bush and Obama administrations, but it seems like Obama is almost more effective
about enforcing it.
I think that's true, and there are a lot of similarities and consistencies between
the Bush administration and the Obama administration.
I remember giving a speech about two years into the Obama administration when someone
asked me about foreign policy, especially as it related to counterterrorism.
And I said, listen, President Obama is even bloodier than George W. Bush was.
President Obama killed more people overseas with drones in his first two years as president
than President Bush killed in eight years as president.
So instead of saying that President Obama is weak on foreign policy and weak on counterterrorism,
on the contrary, he's even bloodier than George W. Bush was.
You're listening to WRT, a public affair.
Gary, welcome to the program.
What is your question or comment?
First of all, thanks for having such an informative guest.
I applaud his courage to come on and say these very truthful things.
My question to this esteemed guest is several.
First of all, to what extent do you think Israel is driving our foreign policy to?
I think you're going to confirm my idea that Obama was a Trojan horse put in by the
elites because the way they ran him against Hillary, a lot of the progressives drank the
Kool-Aid and, of course, he was a Trojan horse.
And lastly, other people, entities that are getting off, Scott, free are the bankers
who have bankrupted the country and the military industrial complex taking all the
wealth out of the country.
So we have no high-speed trains, no decent roads, and no decent future.
Thank you.
Wow, thank you for those excellent questions.
And I'm essentially just going to agree with you.
There really is no country in the world that has as much of an effect on U.S.
foreign policy as israel
we have of course uh... a very long and deep and abiding relationship with
israel but the israeli's really
have a lobby in washington that is
that is unparalleled by any other country the world
and we have a lot of elected officials
in the congress
who uh... really way
what a policy is going to do israel before
weighing what that policy that united states i i i think that that's true
now i will say that the israelis
that the israeli of uh... the coup party at least
uh... is is stridently opposed to
the president some uh... agreement with iran
and he continues to push forward on that rightly so i believe
uh...
it's going to be a lot tougher
convincing congress because israelis have been working on congress for so
long to oppose this deal
at the trojan horse issue
i think the president himself
essentially confirmed that he was a trojan horse
uh... in a book written
uh... after the last election by mark halperin
all when i forget his writing partner
uh... anyway it was a book that that recounted sort of the blow-by-blow of
the of the
obama
romney rate
and he quotes the president and saying two things that were there were
utterly
to me
he said first of all
uh... i never told anybody i was a progressive
which it was just stunning to me because obama was supposed to be the
progressive alternative to hillary clinton
the other thing that he said in that book
that that was so so terrifying
i never thought i'd be so good at killing people
i mean is that really what we want our president to to to be thinking is
that is that
the kind of president we want to have an office
somebody who's very comfortable killing people
and someone who's very comfortable
campaigning on a lie
and then showing his true colors once he's elected
i was very disappointed
on that note let's take a little break you're listening to w r t public
affair this is your rashkin and uh... for sure break we're going to continue
conversation with
john karyakou former say analyst and case officers in a senior investigator for
the senate foreign relations committee
and account of terrorism consultant for a bc news and author will be right back
at
the
We're back, you're listening to WRT Public Affair.
This is Yuri Rashkin and my guest is John Kiriakou.
And one of the subjects of today's program really is this book that is published by the
Navy Institute, Rebottle, the say a response to the Senate Intelligence Committee's study
of its detention and interrogation program written by, the essay is contributed, I guess, by three
of the last say directors and lots of others, second, third in command in at CIA.
John, do you feel that they're trying to assign blame somewhere else where they're saying
there is no blame or what are they're saying?
Yeah, I think that they're saying there is no blame to go around that, well, George
Tennant has always maintained that the torture program was not torture, that it just didn't
rise to the level of torture, even though people died during the interrogation, that
it didn't result in torture.
Another thing that they're denying, and this is really just so puzzling to me, I don't
understand their explanation, the Senate torture report did not dwell on the handful
of so-called enhanced interrogation techniques that had been approved by the Justice Department.
What the Senate torture report focused on was instances and evidence where CIA interrogators
went over and above what had been allowed by the Justice Department, things like rectal
rehydration using hummus, which I would call sexual assault, things like obstruction
of justice, things like the cold cell that had not been approved where Huff and Gould died
of exposure.
I'd like to know why that doesn't constitute torture to George Tennant, and I would like
to know why the people who carried out these techniques have not been prosecuted.
John, you were talking about the different values that existed in the 1990s and up
until September 11th.
How do we instill those values back into CIA so that should another command come down through
political channels, people just, I don't know, quit in mass?
Or is that what happened in 2002, 2003, and they were replaced with more pliable operatives?
No.
You know what, it's not really about the operatives, it's about Congress and congressional
oversight.
The CIA, I mean, the average CIA employee is an automaton.
He'll do what he's told by his superiors, and his superiors will do what they're told
by the Congressional Oversight Committee.
So if the policy is to respect human rights, they'll respect human rights.
If the policy is to institute a torture program, they'll start torturing people.
So what we really need is congressional leadership, and we don't have it.
Diane Feinstein, until just, you know, the last two years, was probably the CIA's
greatest cheerleader on Capitol Hill.
Whether it was during the Obama administration or the Bush administration before it, she was
a great, great friend to the CIA, and she essentially approved of anything the CIA wanted to do.
What do you feel was her motivation?
Well, I believe you are the likes of Frank Church or Paul Wellstone.
I'm sorry, what do you feel were her motivation, Senator Feinstein's motivations for such
strong support of CIA?
Well, I've always been a believer in the idea that the CIA is very, very good at informally
recruiting the people that it needs, especially on Capitol Hill.
You kind of make it sound sinister, you know?
Well, it is.
I mean, the CIA, every CIA operations officer is trained in manipulation, and the only way
that you can get ahead in life at the CIA is to recruit people, recruit them over to your
side.
So you've got a new senator who's on the House or Senate, I'm sorry, a new member of Congress
who's either on the House or Senate Intelligence Committee, they've never been on the committee
before, and then they see their very first blue border report, or they get their very
first classified briefing, or their very first look at a sensitive operation overseas,
and you know you've hooked them.
You've made them a part of the team, and they want more.
They want to be part of that club, part of that exclusive group that knows the country's
darkest secrets.
And so you draw them in on this way.
I mean, the CIA...
You know, even if the secrets were elicited, you know, through torture and are probably
conceivably erroneous to begin with, people still are seduced by that sense of power
and being, you know, having the key to the executive bathroom, you know?
It is the key to the executive bathroom.
And don't forget that the torture regime, the enhanced interrogation techniques were
all approved by the Senate and House Oversight Committee.
So the members of Congress who were serving on those committees at the time are in
this up to their necks just like the CIA leadership is, even though they may deny
it.
They knew about it.
They did nothing to stop it.
They approved of it.
It sounds a little bit like still you are absolving CIA itself off the responsibility
by saying that the employees are, you know, automatons, as you mentioned, as you
said, refer to, but their responsibility is with Congress.
What about the employees?
Yeah.
You know, one of the great disappointments for me is we signed the Senate torture
report that there were CIA officers in the field who were cabling back and
saying, this is torture.
I don't like it.
I don't want to do it.
I want to come home.
Okay.
And then those officers were allowed to come home, but nobody ever talked.
Nobody ever went public and said, this is wrong.
We shouldn't be doing it.
I fault them for that.
But really I placed the greatest fault on the CIA's leadership.
We had people in positions of leadership, and you named them at the start of
this program that I would consider to be sociopaths.
I would consider to be people who are unable to operate within the confines of the law.
I think that they committed grave crimes against the Constitution, and I think it's a
terrible
terrible slapped to the constitution to the american people that the
administration won't prosecute them
you're listening to the or t monday edition of a public affair this is your
rashkin and my guest is former cia counterterrorism officer john kiri akku
well john i'm trying to uh... kind of wrap my mind around this because
uh... the the statement you just made basically calling the last three uh...
chairs uh... you know office a sociopath
uh... you know because once is an occurrence two is a coincidence and
three i believe is a pattern
does it mean that you need to be sociopath to be in charge of cia or just to
work there
but you know what the i a psychiatrist once told me
that the cia
peak to hire
people who have sociopathic tendencies
specifically sociopath
but people with sociopathic tendencies isn't like they'll they'll finish the
job on the inside
yeah and you know they're comfortable walker working in
legal or moral or ethical gray areas
uh... you know they're comfortable breaking into people's houses or
offices and planting bugs
we're carrying out operations against individuals
but it's very hard to weed out
the sociopath from those with sociopathic tendencies because sociopath
have no conscience they have no ability to empathize
and so they can very easily pass a polygraph exam
and what you end up having
it like in any major corporation you know where where
psychologist and psychiatrist will tell you that it's the sociopath who rise to
the top and become the c e o of the corporations the same thing happened
at the cia
the one to keep getting promoted and promoted promoted
are the ones who are comfortable breaking the law
alright so that's what happened so then to cut you know to the bigger
picture do we do you feel cia is needed
in the first place
i always believed
a cia was needed
until about five years ago
the more i thought about it the more i read about it the more i realized that
that former senator
annual patrick moinehan of new york was right
when he said in nineteen seventy six
that the cia should be
broken up
that human intelligence can be done
by the military which has a defense human services uh... division
that analysis can be done by the defense intelligence agency and the
state department uh...
uh... bureau of uh...
of intelligence research
and certainly science and technology that the cia does can be done in any
number of of federal agencies
so i i've come to the conclusion that
we really don't need to see i anymore
now through uh...
ever snowden's revelations one of the things that big part of the
american public has learned is about the active role that
and i say plays
uh... in in spying on american citizens and in general involvement in spying
count is that
relationship work between cia ns a and if you don't need cia do you need ns a
or all of those intelligence services just are are not really helpful to art
really to our security
you know it was illegal
for for the ns a to intercept
not just the communications of american citizens but of any
uh... quote quote u.s. person that is
any american or
for a national in the united states on a uh... on a green card
legal president
that held up
until september eleventh
and with the passage of the patriot act
ns a attorney
in cahoots with the justice department office of legal counsel
twisted the law
to allow ns a for the very first time ever
to spy on american citizens
it's even written in ns a charter
that it's not permitted to spy on american citizens
and so with the passage of that
ill-conceived in poorly named patriot act
uh... we've created a uh...
domestic surveillance monster
that i believe is in violation of of our own constitution
you know in a perfect world i would want an ns a
to spy on foreign countries and to intercept
you know electronic communications
and that's what it did until the purple
and now it seems that it is focused almost solely
on dragnet collection of american communications
the cia and ns a historically
have had very close relationship
uh... even
way down at the analytic level at the working level
i i assume that that
still the case and
i think that's very dangerous
now with it though the revelations we also know that and it has brought in
most of our major
telecommunications company
uh... a tnp had a very close working relationship with
uh... with ns a as did you know for rising and and others
that's really what we should fear
if there's going to be any kind of reform in congress
i think the congress should look at ns a even before it looks at cia
i think that the most immediate danger
alright now uh... john you speak to a lot of people who are true you know i
ask you the same questions over and over and i imagine you find certain ways to
explain certain concepts
that are in your opinion are effective in trying to get the point across
and and here's the situation that i ran into with with this topic is when i put
out the word but that i'll be you know speaking about torture
and is short torture ever appropriate or effective
uh... the comment that i got which i think is really typical is
if it saves lives through info gathered heck yes
the problem is filtering that info
i'm on the fence here rights you know for a minor social media
how do you get over this if it saves lives when we know it doesn't work
yeah it
it nobody is able to point to any
instances any evidence at all where torture has saved a single
american life
psychiatrists will tell you believe me
the cia is chock full of psychiatrists
but psychiatrists will tell you that
a victim of torture will tell his torture absolutely anything
he thinks that person wants to know just to get the torture to stop
we had haleh sheikh muhammad
who was really the the
the leader of the nine eleven attack the the creator of the idea of the
nine eleven attack
we we tortured him and he admitted to things that
crime that he couldn't possibly have
have committed
even admitted to bring daniel pearl
uh... an american journalist in in pakistan
in two thousand two
we know that he didn't murder daniel pearl
uh... so really it does nothing but it
but then
cia analysts
down
the wrong road
looking for
conspiracies that don't exist
for evidence of the tax that
just aren't there
it's just a bad policy
you're listening to w r t on the issue of public affairs if you're asking we have
a few remaining moments with uh... our guest today john carry out is a former
say counterterrorism officer
uh... john what do you feel if you well if our listeners if you have just a
few minutes to give us a call we have uh... lines open six oh eight two five
six two zero zero one
john what do you feel you ultimately will learn from this because every
experience is an opportunity to learn lessons what what lessons have you
learned from this for yourself
uh... boy a lot i've learned a lot
you know i always trusted my government i i spent nineteen years in federal
service and
went to college here in washington got both of my degrees in washington i i
really believe that in the end
uh... truth always wins and that's just not
that's just not the case
i always believed in justice
and that's also not the case
uh...
i maybe i was maybe i was naive to think that
government operate the way it's supposed to operate for the for the benefit of
the american people it it doesn't
again with that
uh... if you see something say something that's what the government always says
right
whether it's a backpack or whether it's government committing a crime
you have to stand up and you have to pay enough
this is wrong
so that's another thing i learned
is there anything going to get they did the right thing
looking back do you feel that there is anything that you would have liked to
have done differently you know i once again to uh... at which no one's reference
you know the
you know going to hong kong then to russia now of course the irony of fate is
that he's
stuck in probably one of the least free countries in the world and uh...
uh... what do you feel you could have done differently or wanted want
now to have done differently than
there are two things that i that i
should have done differently
i should have hired an attorney before i went on a bc
uh... especially an attorney skilled in whistleblower protection
i wish i had known to do that
the second thing is uh...
i i spoke to the fb i and i should never ever have spoken to the fb i
it was an hour and twenty minutes into that conversation before i realized that
they were investigating me
they weren't asking for my help in an investigation
the investigation was of me
and so i told it though both of those things
higher the best
uh... whistleblower attorney you can find
and don't ever
ever speak to the fb i under any circumstances
you know there's a video i think out there on uh... in the youtube land that
says and never talk to police you're adding adding to that never talk to fb i
not unless your attorney sitting right there next to you
all right and in you know the part of the reason that we were able to
connect is your opposition to this book that's coming out so i'd like to give you
one more opportunity to kind of summarize about the
the re-bottle by the
say, you know, collection of former directors, anything you wanted to say that people should
know about this book.
I think this book is nothing more
than an attempt
for a group of discredited individuals
to try to save their reputations.
Torture does not work.
It has never worked. It has never disrupted an attack.
It has never saved an American life and it has
no place in American policy.
John Caraccio, going forward, what are you looking to work on? Do you ever hope to
put this behind you?
Yeah, you know, I really hate being the torture guy,
although that seems to be what I've become.
I'm working now at the Institute for Policy Studies, a highly respected
and
old think tank here in Washington,
looking at issues like torture and intelligence community reform and prison
reform even.
So I intend to stay there
and I've been speaking
around the country, mostly at colleges and universities, but also before peace
groups and a couple of non-profits.
So I hope to continue doing that as well.
And I'm going to teach a class in the ethics of intelligence operations
that I developed at the university level.
And I've got two books
getting ready to come out. One is called Letters from Loretto,
which is based on a series of blog posts that I wrote from prison.
And the next is called
Doing Time Like a Spy, How the CIA Taught Me to Survive and Thrive in Prison,
which is sort of a more fun
book full of
anecdotes.
So kind of not your worst, you know, what to do in a worst case scenario
about how to get through life, you know, how to think like Einstein or how
to think like a CIA spy.
That's right. You know, when you go to prison,
the first thing you want to do is make sure that you stay at the top of the social heap.
That sounds like most any organization, doesn't it?
John, I want to thank you for being on the program today. John Kiriakou is
an individual who's been through a lot and I very much appreciate his ability
to connect with us today and share his experience and answer your calls.
You're listening to WRT Public Affair.
This is Yuri Rashkin
and I want to also thank Holly for producing, for engineering the program
and Sarah for
engineering,
producing. Take care.